# Aleksandr Zalesov

Principal Software Engineer / Team Lead

Ritterlandweg 1-3 13409 Berlin Germany +4915737654395 zallesov@gmail.com

### **SUMMARY**

I'm a software developer with nearly two decades of hands-on experience, spanning roles from Principal Developer to CTO across startups and enterprises such as Soundcloud and Volkswagen. In my career, I have faced the challenges of running huge software systems at scale and high load as well as managing teams of developers of various sizes and levels.

Now I'm seeking a leadership role in a startup or mid-size enterprise where my diverse skill set can drive significant growth and innovation.

#### **KEYWORDS**

- Methodologies: SCRUM, TDD, Clean Code, SOLID
- Languages: Typescript, NodeJS, Python, Scala, Java
- Cloud providers: Google Cloud Services, Amazon Cloud Services, Microsoft Azure
- ML/AI: Tensorflow, LLM, ChatGPT, LLAMA2, HuggingFace, Replicate, Whisper, VertexAI
- DevOps: Docker, Kubernetes, AWS Lambdas, GCS cloud functions, Terraform
- Databases: Postgresql, Cassandra, Firestore, Redis, etc.
- Messaging systems: Kafka, rabbitMQ, PubSub, etc.
- Frameworks: React, NextJS, AkkA, ZIO, LangChain, Redux Zustand
- CI/CD: CircleCI, Google Cloud Build, GitHub Actions

### **EXPERIENCE**

### **2Meters**, Berlin — CTO

March 2020 - PRESENT

### https://2meters.app https://manage.2meters.app

2meters is a SaS solution to manage customer queues and appointments on-site.

In meters, I am a founding CTO. Together with a team of friends, we've built a service that is now used on 5 continents. We have raised some investment that allowed us to hire a team of engineers to build the product.

Even being involved in the project part-time I

- Build an independent team of developers who can act without micromanagement.
- Organize the work process in a manageable and predictable manner applying agile practices.
- Teach my developers all I know about good software development practices. Which led to short PR review cycles and better code quality.

- Facilitated company-wide meetings for knowledge transfer and planning
- Communicated with leads and clients identifying their requirements
- Define requirements for the subcontractors for developing marketing landing sites

As a result, the service is used by thousands of users daily and generates stable revenue.

Stack: Firebase and Google Cloud Services, React, TypeScript, NextJS

### **Super-Real**, London/Berlin — Principal Software Engineer

June 2023 - Aug 2023

https://super-real.co/ https://super-real.co/zall

Super-real is a web-based chat where anyone can chat with celebrities or influencers backed by an AI.

With a team of only 3 devs part-time, we have achieved an incredible outcome in just two months leading the project to production worldwide and generating revenue. My responsibilities were everything AI-related

- Prompt engineering to better impersonate a persona.
- Saving and retrieving embeddings (the facts) about the persona
- Experimenting with different LLMs to achieve a better performance.
- Training the model to mimic the spoken style better

Identify when the user asks about certain topics to provide additional paid content (images, voice messages)

In this project, I've acted as an individual contributor accompanied by just two of my fellow very senior developers.

Stack: Lang-Chain, ChatGPT, LLAMA2, TypeScript, Google Cloud Services, NextJS

Footnote. My time with Super-real, Snubes, and Zapp should be considered as single employment. Projects were developed in parallel by the same core team.

# **Snubes**, Berlin — Software Developer Team Lead

Jan 2023 - Aug 2023

https://snubes.com/ https://app.snubes.com/

Snubes provides services to assess and track the performance of call centers' individual agents and projects overall using AI.

Together with my team, we've

- Set up a phone call transcription pipeline using a modified version of OpenAI's Whisper model (WhisperX)
- Develop another pipeline to analyze transcription produced by Whisper to categorize, flag, and act on them.
- Deployed a hub that received call data from various call center vendors using various techniques. (SFTP, webhooks, pull APIs)
- Built an internal leaderboard for the sales team to track the performance of individual sales managers
- Set up monitoring solutions and CI/CD pipelines for the whole company

I've inherited the team with no coding standards or principles. I had to let go most of it keeping only the motivated ones. After setting up the essential agile processes and best practices (CI/CD, code review, git-flow,

Stack: Google Cloud Services, React, Typescript, Python, ChatGPT, Whisper, VertexAI

## **Zapp**, London/Berlin — Software Developer Team Lead

June 2021 - Dec 2022

### https://tryzapp.co.uk

Zapp is a groceries delivery service at that time operating in UK, Netherlands and France.

I was managing a team of varying size up to 6 people. We had our fingerprints in every codebase in the company. Starting from the consumer app ending with ops infrastructure terraform code.

My team and I were contributing to

- An internal tool for warehouse and city managers called Zappboard. It aggregated data from every other system and presented it in an actionable way.
- Last mile delivery software. It showed the state of the order and rider's fleet on the map. And it was also deeply integrated with the Zappboard.
- Tools for scanning and picking orders in the warehouse
- Train an ML model to predict the delivery time based on over 40 parameters and integrate it into the ordering process.
- Integrating with other storefronts like Uber Eats and Deliveroo
- Contributed to the development of company-wide monitoring tools and ops infrastructure.

Besides that, I was the responsible person for organizing knowledge sharing in the company. I've organized and facilitated tech-talks and demos. Also planned on-call rotations.

Stack: Firebase and Google Cloud Services, React, TypeScript, Tensorflow, Python, Terraform

# MOIA (Volkswagen), Berlin/Hamburg — Senior Software Engineer

Mar 2019 - Jan 2020

### https://www.moia.io/en

MOIA is a company under the Volkswagen umbrella. The main challenge there was to optimize supply for the demand to match a particular van to a particular order and also re-distribute vans across the city to decrease waiting time.

### I have contributed to

- A real-time simulation service that simulated the vans behavior based on real-life demand data.
- Step by Step simulation service. This service could simulate a week of real-life fleet behavior. This service was part of a framework to assess different ride-sharing algorithms.
- A "dispatching" service that aggregated the state of the fleet in real-time showing the vans, their routes, and customers on the map. This service was the backbone that connected vans, customers, ride-optimization services, and fleet managers.

Stack: AWS, Scala, ZIO, AKKA, Reddis, Amazon IOT

# **Zalando**, Berlin — *Software Engineer*

Nov 2017 - Aug 2018

### https://zalando.de

Zalando is Fashion e-commerce service

In my short time in Zalando, I've contributed to a few internal projects.

- Product image labeling with AI. Service described the item by "looking" at its pictures
- Product image verification. Service checked that the item has all of the required images and that the images are in the right format. White background, shoes facing right and taking 75% of space, etc.

Stack: AWS, Scala, ZIO, Kafka

## **Soundcloud**, Berlin — Software Engineer

Feb 2013 - Jul 2017

#### https://soundcloud.com

In my almost 5 years in soundcloud I probably got the biggest skill boost in my career as I was working shoulder to shoulder with the most talented people from around the world. I've also learned how a healthy and pleasant work environment can look like.

Some highlights from those years are

- I am the man behind the canonical soundcloud audio player on the web.
- I've also contributed to mobile audio players.
- In the copyright protection team, we developed a pipeline that identified and automatically took down any upload that infringed someone's copyright.
- I've become a scala developer and learned Functional Programming techniques.

That was probably the most technically challenging and highly loaded project I've contributed so far. Ask me about it.

Stack: Scala, Java, JavaScript, Cassandra, Kafka, AWS, Docker, Kubernetes.

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Novosibirsk State Technical University**

Sep 2003 - Mai 2008

Specialist degree (Masters) in Math and Computer Science.

### **LANGUAGES**

Russian — *Native* English — *Professional* German — *B*2